Good afternoon thanks thank it thanks everyone for joining us after a long day of
sessions it's been a super exciting day we're really happy to be here this afternoon talking about
io t my name is sam george I run the
...efforts within the cloud enterprise
division I also want to thank everyone that's joining online this is my paul
...you should be the one presenting cloud and I...but it's the opposite so,
go ahead and introduce...everybody I'm steve to share up
...forty four-years-old and finally almost not self-conscious about my
...anymore...really appreciate that censure
...welcome I know it's five pm your choices between
cocktails and us and thank you all for being here those of you that are attending via the web
we trust you've already cradle the beverage of your choice so with that.
Patrol all right let's do it...
We are going to.
Ok.
So, today we're going to be talking about the overall...opportunity
...you haven't been living under hockey probably heard about internet of things and what a big opportunity it
is we're going to sort of reiterate that also going to talk about the plans that we've got across
...your and windows for io t microsoft is extremely committed to io
t we think it's an incredibly important opportunity and,
it's something that you're going to see a lot more from us going forward?
...we've talked about coyote for a while but I have...not really a
new thing necessarily we've been doing imbedded for many years and often people come to
me and say
...t thing like I've been sending data from my devices forever and I've had all these little devices
...work with...things long long-time so why...having a new conversation
...ty...worthy...you know, this room filling up with so many of
you I think the few different things one is the cost of hardware
in a lot of domains is kind of asymptotically going to zero like literally
...are some cases where you can get, you know, the marginal cost of producing a new piece of hardware over
large manufacturing run is almost negligible so,
that's just made it very easy we can crank out hardware today...many domains almost
as almost as cheaply as we crank out software in the past.
The other thing that's changed is the pervasive
nys of connectivity used to be back in the day that connectivity was
...bandwidth very slow...very expensive it was very hard to get a
...high-bandwidth connection today between you know,
three-g for...mobile data as well as prob wi-fi coverage data
is almost there and you can kind of depend on that for building new solutions tools
are much simpler than they have been in the past whether we're talking about the software side through visual
studio or through a lot of what's going on the open-source...through the hardware side through things like our
do we know and raspberry...they're just making it very easy for people to develop hardware
software solutions and the advent of new cloud-based solutions that we can
...these together it's no longer just about these devices in the world
kind of working independent of one another if these devices connected to one another connected to the
cloud and producing a solution that really exceeds the sum of
all parts so all these things these kind
...new trends generate these new solutions and people are saying the value
of these new solutions which is kind of fueling the demand for more and it's become this innovator virtuous site.
So, the world of io...in two thousand ten just five years
ago looks a lot different than the
world of coyote in two thousand fifteen.
You see a much richer ecosystem we think this is accelerating considerably
especially right now we think by twenty, twenty ths a look even dramatically different.
You know, there's some laws of physics in our space and you know,
the first graph you see moore's law...probably most of us in this room
are kind of either talk to people about this or worthy year over year beneficiary
of moore's law building software solutions that take advantage of the fact that
computers are getting increasingly capable...yearbecause transistor density doubles there
...that machine can do a little bit more every time that doubling occurs every eighteen months to a
couple of years on the far-right side of this slide you seewhat's called...law a
...economist to think working over at stanford these days and this is a little bit different than more
...this isn't about transistor density this is about our and if you
see the regularity of this curve and check out the beginning date of this curve
it's like the late nineteen forties since the late nineteen forties
our ability to do you instruction processing for a particular a
particular unit of energy is kind of doubling about every year-and-a-half so what that means
if you if you run the numbers on that you end up with
...machine in ten years can do twice the work with the same battery of
a machine today about every ten years we get about double
battery efficiency based on the compute load...the middle there's this little thing called metcalf...bob
...guy that invented ethernet any came up with this law that says that the
value of any communication network is proportional to the square of
the number of participants of that network so every time we had another...that
network of communication value kind of grows by another square and,
you know, we could think about this in terms of io...things a little bit more a little bit more future
e but I like to think about this and old-school way if you think about the telephone
...the telephone became...super valuable communication network when you
could rely on the fact that everybody had one and I think we're heading that way with coyote we can rely
on the fact that things just know-how to talk to each other and...the cloud.
There are a lot of estimates about how big this is going to be some of them or, you know,
very grandiose some of them are conservative you know,
gartner estimates that the btwenty five billion connected things by twenty,
twenty.
And, I dc is estimating a seven-point two trillion-dollar impact on the economy whatever it is you
...in your crystal ball we're convinced that we're in the midst
of the next generation of computing and it's going to be big either way.
Let's talk about what microsoft is doing priority one of the reasons why samurai both really
like working in the spaces united when I work together a lot to try and figure out what
is what can we do that comprehensive ranging from the smallest devices through to
large devices through to massive hyper scale...enabling our customers to
really build solutions that matter to the world today so on the windows side which is
where I spend most of my time we come from twenty years of history in this space through
...through windows embedded your windows ce...some our past work
in automotive lots of different device categories who can have an opportunity to see
this space of evolve over time we made a bunch of mistakes on the way that we've learned from so
we're eager to kind of bake all those learning's into what we're doing today with windows tent.
One of the things that will focus on throughout several presentations on io
t on windows and build this year is one platform and you heard
...say that earlier today it's kind of one platform depending
...matter if it's hollow lens or raspberry pies
or windows desktop or phone and you can extend that the
io t additions whether you're building and I apps raspberry pies
that depot salmon I will show you later whether building something for this little tiny border
...building something for pc phone laptop or some, you know,
mri machine atm up sales
...sales terminal it's the same platform it's the same developer platform that using it's the
same driver model...the same application model and it's windows so, you know,
that it's ready to go enterprises it's manageable I like to say it's enterprise ready
but it's also maker friendly the fact that it's got this kind of enterprise level infrastructure
built in but we're working really hard to make the developer platform very accessible to use
...you can easily construct solutions.
And, one of the exciting announcements that we made
...at the windows hardware engineering conference last year is that the sm windows
...core addition for the smallest class of devices will be available free
for both commercial as well as noncommercial device builders thanks so on the
...side where obviously very interested in helping customers build cloud-based
I ot services and solutions we have a set of services today that customers are
...using in broad...deployments and,
I'm going to cover today and then we have a rich roadmap that
includes solutions and finished apps all of these are easy to provision to
use to manage they provision and minutes you page you go you
...you need and very importantly for io t these solutions
and are cloud are globally present because when you talk to customers they
...of their io to deployments are either now or will be global
a global scale and customers don't want to
create one solution for every region that they're in we're putting a big emphasis on
end in security and privacy there was a talk earlier today by commons
...about io...security fundamentals ...course have all the industry best
practices...toolbox and we have some ideas for how to take it
even further we will support windows in a first-class way and there's a lot of great things that we have plan on a
roadmap we also support all the rich
a set of devices and operating systems that exist we sort of a tag line that it's the internet
your things and, that you can extract value from your things so we have rich
support for embed bunch versions of linux ios android and some other real
time operating systems so let's talk about cashmere
going to cover as your for the next few slides are going to go back to steve and,
he's going to cover windows in detail ok?
So, I'm going to coverio...device
and cloud patterns the patterns that we tend to see again and again in io t in io
t solutions also going to cover the set of services that we have today and how customers
are using them got a couple customer stories that are fun to talk about and then I'm going to talk about the
...sweet and what we're doing with that?
All right so.
I ot is since it's nascent since it's a new thing and, in some ways of course it's
all-new because m...been around for a long-time but there are some forces that are interesting and
enter creating this phenomenon we call io...but,
when you ask someone what I ot is you tend to get a lot of different
answers based on how many people you ask so we found it really useful in...we're talking with customers to
boil down and io t solution in terms of the patterns that we see and
the value that customers are seeking to extract
from my ot it's a good way to sort of clarify what we mean by ot
...what we're doing for it so we boil it down into really three constituent parts the first
part of courses around device connectivity in management the second is around analytics
...finding insights and I ot data
and then operational rising those and the last is having them code connect
into your business and being able to see and interact with these io...solutions and I'm going to cover each one
and detail so I'm going to start really simply with a empty cloud and a set
of devices the devices that you see over on the left-hand side are running real
time operating systems today...driver based
operating systems linux windows android ios and we expect
this to sort of proliferate as I mentioned we do consider that
...is the internet of your things so sort of come
as you are we also have a cloud over on the right-hand side that I'm going to fill up with the patterns that we see
...ot as well as a solutions that we've got?
So, our first step in the journey is to talk through the device connectivity and management.
It seems like my clippers dying.
My internet of things isn't working.
Thank you stayed all right so device connectivity and management actually I'll just stand over here
and stuff and say...yeah, totally...I don't...job that's right so,
device connectivity in management so, some devices actually communicate directly with a cloud
...very common pattern today we have a service for this as your event tubs
it extremely high scale telemetry ingestion service you basically
send messages over http.
Or am...p which is the advance message queuing protocol each event
ub supports one million unique publishers and supports over a
gigabyte per second...we've had this in-service since beginning of the
year generally available preview before that today on average we're doing
about eighteen billion messages per day worldwide through all of the event
tubs that we have this is changing pretty rapidly about a month ago when I was presenting this
...at ten billion so, we're seeing a very sharp increase in the number of both devices
that are connected as well as other services that are connected because you can use event tabs for
other things including telemetry from the web sites and things like that.
We're doing about sixty terabytes per day ingesting into asher worldwide to these ot
hubs as well so this is an interesting pattern were devices are sending telemetry
to a cloud gateway it's not the only pattern in fact some devices
don't belong on the open internet there's some devices that are very low powered where if you put them on the
open internet and receive commands for many inbound traffic you probably not
going to like what happens next to that device so very common pattern that you see and io
...is that of an intermediate field gateway and this is
much of a pattern as it is a device so, for example, we consider a cell
...to be a field gateway and there's customers that are delivering solutions over bluetooth
...to sensors on devices that connect through
smartphone there's also of course industrial-strength routers and feel gateways
foreman interesting security boundary as well they can provide a sense advice
or us capability of isolation in the security talk we talk about this pattern we call
...cystic community communication where the feel gateway is responsible
for the isolation of those devices another interesting pattern that we see is that
feel gateways do protocol adaptation and translation so in into m
and I...been around for a long-time as I said earlier there's a lot of protocols including custom
ones...customers have invented or of used a lot of them don't belong on
the open internet so, protocol adaptation is a really interesting pattern
for extracting value from those devices that have already been deployed so,
this is sort of the first part of this device to cloud patterns and customers
do find value in this and like I said many of the
examples that we've got today that I'm going to be talking about uses pattern of
a cloud gateway but there's additional needs that we have an io t?
You have the need for command and control to be able to issue a command to a device and to be able to know
whether received it you need to be able to keep track of the identity of all these devices and
preserved that identity when you're replacing devices you need
...device registry that includes all the capabilities and assets and things like that the device
has and you also need device management as we said in our soc in
our security talk what you can't update you can't secure so being able to update
operating systems and firmware and software that's running on devices is very important
and io...and of course it ranges in your security
...needs will of course range but we think device management is a very important part of bio
...so I'm excited to announcer coming with the asher ot
...will be previewing this year we have an additional service that will be available with the ot
...the ot hub and there's a talk on this is well this week so the io
t hub is supports bidirectional device
to cloud connectivity it will support up to ten million devices so...sort of
...extreme scale io...ingestion service and command...
command service exports command control it has a device registry as
well as maintains device identity and it will support device management so you'll be able
to manager devices which is really important when you start getting different scale of audiotape you don't
actually want to go around and flash devices because there's a lot of them ...support http and
amp as well as in q tt and extensibility mechanism.
So, labels these interaction patterns right sam where one device might
...some signals send that to a cloud service and
...service can maybe predict that something is going to go roaring and have some other
devices?
Act accordingly absolutely so,
as part of our commitment were not just building cloud gateways and cloud components
...also delivering st...for devices so,
we'll have an open-source agent framework ...will be available at
it runs on a variety of real time operating systems a variety of linux
variance windows of...android ios and,
like I said this will be...open-source project
...will continue to innovate it's easy to use is not required this is just something that
makes it easy to get started we support standard protocols
...cloud gateway so the way this is built is there's a set of cross-platform
c code that we've got...as well as like any good cross-platform code we've got
it os abstraction layerwith the set of os bindings and the nice thing about this approach
is that to move to another platform all you have to do is create a new os
...an example of what we abstract in the operating systems are things that are different
like memory management threading and networking and things like that and then will provide a set of
...api on top both see api net api is java api
...as well as a node library for javascript api is the see api
our providing one
...run in very memory constrain devices rc api actually
runs and kilobytes of memory not megabytes of memory so very small and yet has all that
rich functionality there's a lot of functionality built into this batching
retry the extensible encoding extensible serialism asian and things like that?
Array moving on so most folks don't wake up in the morning and say I want to
connect a bunch of devices to the cloud just for fun there's something that they want to get out of it
and this will...and, here's what most folks so,
on the device connectivity and management there's a lot of interesting things companies are doing already
by just monitoring remote devices a great example is fleet management if you can
...your fleets...were all your things are you can keep control of them but,
what we see is that customers the value that they're starting to extract alibi
...starts to really shine when you get into analytics
and operational rising those analytics so let me give some examples, for example,
in fleet management there's a really interesting thing is whereas if, you know,
...all of your fleet where if, you know,...the rapture fleet or travelling on and,
the incidence that your fleet has on those routes like and things get stolen you can
start doing intelligent routing and traffic routing and things like that the pattern that you tend
to see in this stage of our journey?
Looks like I'm going to have to go back to the keyboard.
Thank you steve the first the first stage...journey analytics and operational
...insights is where your finding the interesting things interesting
...into your data to either our new services are
improve those things so,
we have a rich set of services available today as your html site map reduce measure
...which are unique approach to machine learning our biif
...rich visualizations as well as
your data factory and just announced today as your data lake...pipelining
...data warehousing companies use this to find those insights I'll
give an example here which is...which is an elevator company have one-point-one
million elevators worldwide and for each one of...a bunch of different models that they service
of those elevators and for each one of those elevators what they had a set servicing
schedule what turns out that if, you know, things like how much it was used and
what how much weight was in it and the operating temperature of things you can much
musing machine learning you-can much more accurately predict how much servicing it needs and
...in most cases reduce the amount of servicing while providing better up times and offering
up time guarantees that's a good example of finding those insights it's not just enough to
finals insights once you have those insights you actually have to operational...those you need to do
something in real-time we have to services today for this we have as
your stream analytics which is a really cool service on complex
event processing that has a really nice simple sequel syntax where you can treat
an extreme volume telemetry scale as if it were static table
...issue sequel queries that includes tumbling windows
and averages and things like that and then you can go and
saved those on the to blob storage we also have a measure hd insight
...storm which is simply apache storm as a hosted offering so,
this is really interesting because right because everyone
...adders the windows cloud measures very friendly to open-source and linux it's a
great growing workload that we've got a measure html site storm is a great complex
and that processing framework so, we fully support that...io
to solutions as well and then the last part of our tour around the analytics an operation...
insights is so that pattern works really well that complex
...processing works really well if you're dealing with homogenous sets and things
like elevators orf a fleet and you're and you're, you know,
what you're looking for when devices in the real-world start to form hierarchies
and graphs things start to get complicated like
...there's logical parent-child relationships so imagine, for example,
if you're doing building maintenance forcompany this the
scale of microsoft where you've got buildings all over the globe campuses all over the globe
each campus has a collection of buildings in each building as a collection of room's...
as collection of sensors which they really do for all sorts of things from temperature to movement
or whatever and you want to implement essentially manage system for
doing things like turning on the lights when...critical amount of people are in the building to
do that one approach to do that is to...is to tag every single
sensor and then just somehow be able to aggregate sensors a
much more natural way to do that is to build an object model and to take
...that high-volume telemetry scale and bind it to that object model and
have that object model be able to be distributed
throughout a cluster so today we announced service fabric which is our next generation platforms
...service empowers a lot of the services that we do
including event tubs coyote hub and document db and sequel server and
...time and a whole bunch more and it's a massive scale service that elastic
...scales up and we think it's very important for the internet of things in
this particular pattern it allows you to runsort of distributed business logic
a across all of the...state of your io t devices?
So, moving on...the next phase of our journey last the last phase
...course need to be able to visualize data coming from the solutions and control
these solutions these solutions don't exist in a vacuum they exist
in businesses so, for example,
when you detect that and elevator needs servicing ahead of schedule it's not just about knowing
that it's about opus opening a customer relations record it's about rolling
truck it's potentially about ordering apart so there's a there's a workflow
...required so we supporta bunch of services for this from dynamics
tobits talk servers and to notification...we also have rich third-party
extensibilityfor all sorts of other business process workflow and,
then of course we have app service and websites...mobile services and
abridge services so this kind of gives us gives you an idea of how we
ci ot and sort of the end-to-end that we have the...that we have on io
...what customers are doing with it so if we move on so these are the services that we've
got today we've got the set of services for machine learning to stream analytics
to hd insight data factory and customers are building on all of these today I'm going to
go through a few examples...I'm going to talk about how we're taking this to the next level so the
first opener customer visit is that of
rockwell automation so rockwell as a great company it's been in business for a long
long-time and they're making their journey and io...with us so,
I otrockwell has a deployment annotate deployment for remotely monitoring
gassing well, heads and doing predictive maintenance on those and they have
a lot of really interesting things they can do like they can tell
maintenance history over time they can schedule service visits before anything happens
so you sort of a pattern that you'll see again and again and I...is around predictive something
predicted maintenance predictive stocking using the cloud to predict and drive
efficiencies that weren't possible before go into the next one this is a fun one
the stanford linear accelerator is doing a project with us as well
...streaming io t data through event...industry
analytics to be able to predict using machine learning when components are going
to have problems and to services ahead of time if we go to the next one?
So,no, as your io t presentation would be complete without connected...
So, this is a true story so, we have a great partnership with widgets ewf
widgets too is very much and I ot they have a lot of rich
...and rich products already for io...from
their equal dashboard over to being able to grow fruits and vegetables in
hydra panic labs control by machine learning they have another one which is connected cow and I
love connected cal because to me it really illustrates what the
as the innovation that we're going to seeing-eye ot and the unpredictability that we're going to see and I
ot ok so here's how...cowards so it turns out when cows are
...only an asterisk for a very short window and if you miss that window you have to wait so
...what fidgety...was that if you put an
industrial grade speedometer on a cal and monitor its steps?
You can predict using machine learning you can project with a very high accuracy about ninety eight
percent when it's time to make more cows turns out that's very important and,
it also turns out that two percent of false positives tend to be when the
cows got loose so you kinda want to know that too so,
connected houses a great example from fidgety this is actually been deployed to I think
it's ten farms in japan with really significant heard production
inc improvements ...yes...
So, that's connected...and that really is sort of illustrates the bret for us
and bio t and the unpredictability.
So, for learning more it build we've got a few talks it happened today they will be available
on-demand the microsoft architecture for internet of things I
ut security fundamentals we've got a great talk on events hubs as well as stream analytics
...mellon our by encourage you to check those out
so we've also mentioned that coming soon is the...talk a little bit more about
that right now so today what customers are doing is you're taking the as
your ot services and I'll go and provision quickly and I ot hub...stream analytics instance
and connect them together and we think we can do better we think we can make it so that because we see
a repeated pattern of use cases that customers are doing from
remote monitoring to asset management to predictive maintenance and what we're going to do
any address ot...is allow customers and the as...portal to simply go
...provision those directly and will orchestrate all the services if you're familiar with the as
a resource manager these are...resource manager templates
that provision and we do any code customization that's...these are also finished
absence so they promote they include a set of web app web assets for
monitoring managing and things like that better then also customizable because one of the things
we found is that customers really want the sort of finished apps but then they also really want to
customize them so as you rotate sweetest sort of the best of both worlds there it also provide
...predictable billing so it's very easy to model out your
cobs especially you grow to scale and then finally the nice part about
this is that the same thing that you do your proof of concept with
...scale-up to those ten million devices are beyond we will include a free addition of
these for a certain number of devices so that you know,
if your maker and you want to get started with...to be super easy to...if your business
...doing a proof of concept and you want to sell...concept it'll be very easy to do
...the nice thing is that when you decide to move farther...forward with
the pilot it simply elastic we scales and you pay for...you go
as opposed to I started with something to prove a case and now I have to switch systems
ok so let's go one more all right so I'm going to switch to quick demo I'm just going
...in here?
This is then me all right so I've got a couple I got
a couple boards here that you see I have and arm board
ice I'm sorry I have a free skill board running embed three-point-zero we have
a lot of great partnership going right now with form to our cortex
am classed devices that are literally shipping in the billions today
...running a little are...that's running a little...tosses exactly right and this is running
our open-source frame agent framework we also have a beagle...black running a
boon to snappy so we're also partnering with...canonical...to snappy they have
a very cool little io tty operating system that uses a novel approach to
software updates using containers and then of course we have a raspberry
pi running windows ten and steve's going
to be talking a lot about that and showing some deeper demos so,
we've got this and then over on the other screen we've got a little bit of the assets that
were putting together as part of the larger address ot...will allow you to
provision simulated devices a whole bunch of different devices and download
our software agents and things like that so for today I've got a very simple set
of three devices and I'm going to switch over to it.
Looks like my authentication timed out.
There we go okay so, we have a set of devices so this is sort of
affect little fictitious scenario where each one of these devices represents a vending
machine that's local in the area and it turns out that usually around this time of year that you can see on the
bottom the sales for some reason spike it's almost like there's a whole bunch of people here so,
these really simulate set of vending machines and each one of these vending machines of course gets
sold out pretty quickly and I can simulate what's interesting here is I can simulate this
little button here as I click on it it's actually sending
in a second it's going to send data up to asher and you'll see
our counter increment actually have to refresher.
...being fuzzy right now to ketchup in a second and,
then what I can do is I can actually go back into this
an issue commands backed into the back to the device and this is actually using and
io t hub which will of course support those ten million devices and this
will support rich grouping and tagging and batch commands and all that but today I'm going
to today I'm going to start with something very simple and I'm just going to set a new
price a little higher because...machines are emptying a little too
fast and over on thearm device you're going to see the price change?
We got a new battery great.
And, it's not right now and I'm going to find out why in a second.
Good thing I'm going to...rich...yeah, exactly.
Variety devices yes one of the things that will have the...covers
a as a great visual studio integration with coyote this board
might've frozen I'll tell you what I'm going to come back to this and a reset
the device before before we're done ...if we can switch back to the slides.
There we go...batteries working again so,
we have a great talk on how to interact with the ot sweet with the ot hub from
...dimaggio I believe this one's on-demand so...there's a rich set of demos
that you can go and check out and with that I'm going to turn it over to steve.
Thank you.
Talking about windows.
We'll start with certain announcement it turns out that as a
...thirty six minutes ago we posted the images of windows ten io t
core for both raspberry pie too as well as men aboard max so.
At least that's what I was told was going to happen before I got on stage so we'll assume that all
when according to plan and you'll be able to go up there pleaseagain,
user hotels wi-fi instead of the building wi-fi to get all those all those
disk images so yes we're terribly excited to finally
kind it's been a couple years and the making to get windows ten I ot core out
...sm version of windows and I'll talk a little bit more about the attributes in just
a moment running on devices like the raspberry...you saw up here onstage as well
as intel's been aboard max which is an x eighty-six based x
eighty six base development board also low-cost little bit higher
powered it's not done it's open for your feedback
as a matter-of-fact one of the things that we kind of mind
...wanted to do is get the operating systems
done enough to be able to enable folks to build real devices and,
do real workloads but then also cannot wait to be able to get
...soon as we get to that point so that we can get some feedback that we can use...prioritize...work here and?
Maybe...just depress it really hard I think I'm going to try that I can I
can which were so, when we talk about windows...
space we think about a few different things that windows ten brings?
That are different than what you might find with other operating systems in
space one is this idea of a single consistent platform.
And, again, one operating system that scales across devices whether it's a
single board computer whether it's a complex...set of
...devices a very large-scale the ability to run
universal windows applications one of the things that you'll see in a few different
presentations
throughout the conference is the ability to literally take the same application
and simply change the target from my local machine to my phone to my raspberry
...board to a windows server and have that same application run across this
broad-range of devices even to an xbox or hollow...the other thing that we've done is converge
...windows driver model with universal windows...for years
being a hardware developer in the windows ecosystem was probably more difficult than it
needed to be because if you wanted to support your hardware on windows, you know,
desktop addition of windows, windows embedded standard there was one driver model
you would use to go do that...you want...your harbored be supported for windows mobile devices for
phones that was a different driver model if you want to build small devices may
be on windows ce that was yet another one so you know, I apologize that we made
...right multiple different drivers to kinda get one piece of hardware working
our ecosystem but I'm happy to say that we're well on the way to getting that address now one
universal driver will scale across all of those different platforms?
And, finally the ability to bring new capabilities to
devices you just heard a bunch of great information about how these devices
need to interact with the cloud to build real valuable business
solutions at the same time we want the devices themselves to be awesome to impart of
building awesome devices is I don't just want devices necessarily better sitting passively in the
corner I want devices that I can talk to I want devices that can...that can understand my
gestures want devices that can look at my face and identify me
visually as opposed to me having to offer some manual...credentials.
Windows devices are secure
enterprise great security we bring that same security infrastructure that you would expect to find
a windows server or windows enterprise desktop machine and we bring that even to these
brass reply machines bringing technologies like gps.
For secure boot...four-bit locker to be able to be present on these
the sm I ot devices I've got I've got a friend who's kind of I wouldn't
call him hacker rascal is probably the term he would prefer but,
what he'll do is we'll go look for an...ot device...that's a pretty cool device
pop off the plastic pull out the sd card let me see what I can do with it put the
...card in the computer wow...even bit locker I can do whatever I want with this I can
...I could put some software on it so one of the interesting things about io
...in a lot of these kind of public device scenarios is nobody
...hummus devices a trusted user so you have to
be a careful about security not just information security from a bit credential
standpoint but physical security of advice people can tamper with the devices and do things with
them you probably don't want them to do with them and the ability for mobile devices the
holster multi role profile so if I think about a hand-held that I might use in
a retail scenario...be really great as a retailer...provision one set of
hand-held and based on whoever the user is that picks up that hand-held out of
the charger they can get the right set of apps and they can get the right user interface no matter
whether the manager or clerk or perhaps even a shopper that wants to go do a wedding
registration or something like that from one range of
devices using multi role finally windows devices are born be connected
the connected out-of-the-box connected to peripheralsthere's a retail session on friday
...you can learn about the broad-range of retail peripherals that windows will support out-of-the-box so,
for example, you want to build a...sales solution that incorporates you know,
a cash machine and receipt printer
and barcode scanner a lot of these things today and...usb peripherals
that you plug-in and they light up and work on all additions of windows,
windows devices are interoperable earlier today some of you may have seen gabbing
...talk about all join which is a major investment we're making in windows ten
the idea that devices shouldn't have to conform to some particular
walled garden ecosystem in order to work together and interoperate whether in the home or
in a business devices should, you know, they want to
be free you should be able to have a world where when I buy a couple different devices from two or three different
manufactures they should just know how to work together we should all speak the same protocols in some
ways the fact that today we even think that's novel shows that
we're still evolving in terms maturity but we'll get there and our investment to get
...all join and open standard to be able to enable devices
across operating system to work together locally and connect themselves up to the cloud?
Because these are windows devices you deploy them like windows devices...manage them through,
through mgm or through system center
or into just like you would windows devices they
can participate in windows updates you can get all those management update
security features that you would expect from windows devices and they're ready to be connected to
address...build-out these bigger cloud centric data centric solutions.
Now...had a journey to get to where we arewhat you see here
is not the london to map but rather it is ...for each of the in,... previous
imbedded operating systems that we solve imbedded standard the regular version of
embedded, embedded hand-held and some interesting stations we hit along the way back in
...really excited that we converge the operating system kernel we
kinda had one set of developers writing one set of codes that would
make up the operating system kernel but then we would take that kernel and you know,
and, different things to it for the different windows additions or for xbox
...for phone?
In windows aone we were lana converge application model so we were getting to the point where hey I
can build one application start to get this working across different screens and finally on windows
ten we've landed in the place where it's actually the same
bits these are agnes is actually the same set of bits the same center
...the same set of applications all working together to form
one comprehensive set a solutions now in the device space we also have this windows embedded
compact or ceo lane that I would portray on...a few different
interesting releases along the way now I think ce still has
some high-value for customers because it does things that windows...won't do so,
for example, if you need to build an operating system that has some hard realtime constraints...union operating system that
incorporates those constraints ceo is the way that you would still do that so if you're doing, you
know, some industrial device that has safety constraints that says no really within ten milliseconds
...arm...the stopper cuts the human next two-and-half those kinds of things yes you want to build
those things on an operating system with real time constraints what's more there's a huge ecosystem of
software hardware...built on ce those will continue and we are
investing in tools to enable a lot of those see codes to move over to
windows ten I talked a little bit about this at the windows hardware engineering conference
last month and demonstrated some of the tools that we will use to enable developers to
kind of migrate along the way...
last year this conference I also announced this windows on devices program and we started with the
intel galileo bored and I'm just curious how many of you in the audience the did any of you do you get to
...this galileo...folks the audience that's cool so, yeah,
we were really excited to get windows going on the smallest class of devices
and now we're seeing this windows on devices again is just folded in as a part of windows
ten so windows ten just naturally enables me to target the sm class of device?
Windows ten-ninety comes in three additions
so as I talk about them from the outer most down to the innermost
the outer most is for the largest class of devices and effectively it's a it's a
version of windows enterprise that has the io t bits necessary
for a customization to lock it down to particular apps to lock it down
to particular peripherals so that you can take what is effectively an instance of windows and make
...vending machine or make it atm machine.
The system requirements are that of the desktop windows system
requirements and it supports ux sixty-four x eighty-six.
The next smaller addition of windows as for mobile devices and this is based on
windows mobile so it follows you know,
the chassis requirements of the windows mobile operating system follows the system
requirements in terms of ram and storage of the windows mobile operating system includes the
mobile shell so if I'm building mobile apps I have the ability to use the windows mobile
shell which joe be showed you earlier today and runs on
the arm architecture and then finally the smallest is windows
...core some of you may heard the term happens used to describe this operating system that
was our internal code name which wanted to connect those dots for-you this doesn't have a
shel the shelf for a and coyote core devices the application that you right
that represents the personality of the device it may or may not have a video
screen at all it may be some machine that works in a closet or sits on a wall somewhere and
doesn't have video interaction at all or maybe something that drives a fairly large brian?
Doesn't have any first party microsoft applications so there's no travel and there's no adj,
you know, none of those pieces of software present on this devices the software
that you right plus all the standard operating system components including my ability to
...universal application
...it will run in as little as two hundred fifty six megabytes of ram for
head for...device and in as little as two
gigabytes of storage which is enough to hold the operating system?
All the apps that you would write for the operating system that we're reasonable size and some data
for those applications that would fit and all of that will fit within that
to gigabyte envelope and is supported in either x eighty-six or arm?
Now...few things in addition to these core operating systems what.
Windows updates come with all of these my
ability to use visual studio tools to target all of these again
...works across a broad range of devices I can create...you know,
I talked a little bit earlier about these new user interfaces that we want to build
that is supported and across the across the operating system
envelope talked a little bit about all join you heard sam talk quite a bit about
the asher in terms of how windows folds into the to the as your device
Remember the movies and people
...do this thing I feel like that ok I think I went...one.
This is where you would go to find your copy of windows...for image for either minnow
...max or for raspberry pi to go to windows on devices dot
com and that will take you to the right place and also you'll find not just the
os images there you'll find a bunch of information about the operating systems you'll find sample
projects you'll find a link to a site on get...we've released a whole bunch of both
documentation...projects is open-source you can kind of start to build some cool stuff you'll
hear some talks that will show some of these projects a throughout the course of the presentation earth of
course the conference and I'll hit on a couple a few slides but now I would like to
...like to demo so let us ...google laptop here which I think is input a?
So, I've got a visual studio...actually thank you visual studio so what I've got
here's I've got a visual studio universal application this is
an application that theoretically I could run on any on any windows device but I'm going to run
on my raspberry pot let me show you this raspberry
...really quickly if we can switch to the document projector.
My goal is to give the...team real workout.
Can happen ok so I've got a cool one but I just want to show you the
...board for just a minute kind of introduce you to this bear bore this raspberry
pie to so couple key components there is our that I
use to our the...comes in the form micro usb I've got
...video out html video out so that if I have
...to project video I can do that from this device I've got ethernet I've got
usb ports...I can connect the camera this device there's a serial port on board
with this device they're a bunch of io pins here along the top that I would
use to connect hardware and then drive that hardware via these io pins
...running a broad com are based processor so let me switch away from this
board and let me show you this kind of very cool board that's in a fits
in a nice plexiglass case so this is exactly the same raspberry
...chord but in a nice case and I've got a
little shield that goes with it if I can show you that so then I've got a little whether
shield that's wired to this and this whether she'll has sensors on it that will
take the ambient barometric pressure and the ambient temperature
and the ambient humidity and I can read those things through
...squared see on the on the io...on the raspberry pie and I can, you know,
I can do interesting things with my little home-grown weather st so now let me...to visual studio?
Very nice quick transition and I want to show you a little bit of the code
for this application just to give you a feel for what it
...requires to build something like this so in this case what we've done is I think in this
whether shield and I've got want to show you a little bit of the code the set this
up so what I've done is I've got this gps audio controller class.
And, this is built into windows so gps iowa's
a built-in capability of the windows universal platform are the
universe windows platform I get the default dpi gps audio
...there's only one in this case and then using that I can then start
to configure read and write the gps audio pansto be able to begin a
conversation with this particular shield so kind of doing some initial
...configuration writing some data to the pins and once I've done this
is kind of the one-time configuration for the device once I've kind of configured this device and the shield
for use then I can just go ahead and use and read the data from the shield so
code like this would typically be represented as a library that
usually the shield manufacture would offer you and say hey here's
the library provides a nice class that you can just kinda say you
know, shield dot temperature that sort of thing and be able to read those values out.
If I switch over I just wanted show you how I might be able to
read a property from that so you can see this thing as a property this classes a property called
raw pressure and now you're getting into kind of hardware is ville
where it begins to look like well, you know, if a hybrid is this a little bit as a so now I'm
getting some specific data from this particular shield sensor
and I'm interpreting that data here as in this case a raw measure.
If I just kinda if I just kind of scroll forward
here just want to show you a couple more things I found it was interesting
that the that the altitude was a calculation of barometric pressure so when you see
this application run sometimes you'll see that it looks like we're in death valley because the
...shows below sea level and that's because it's not really,
you know, using a gps to measure altitude or anything like that
it's just using a default calculation based on barometric pressure.
Scrolling forward.
What we've done here is created the shield class that encompasses all of these
all of these attributes on the shield and then we have this whether data structure where...
whether data structure to package up this data and be able to show in the user interface
or do other interesting things with this application?
Now the way the way we've got this working it's kind of interesting
we're writing all of this data out to a file so it's kind of kind of old-school
synchronization the data reading sits in a continuous continuously
running background task so universal platform capability to have this task
...t device that always runs that never goes away just keeps running and
that's what's reading the sensor values about once a second and then periodically
or for each reading in fact we take that and we stored away to a file and then
the user interface for this application which I'll show you simply looks at that file and then outputs the
content that file to be able to say
...the what the current values are let me.
Yeah,...there's a piece of this that I want to show you that has to do with the cloud before I do that
I just want to run this p so running it really is a simple as, you know,
hitting at five...clicking the green arrow in visual studio this is a windows computer this
little raspberry pi so things like remote debugging that we can take for granted in the windows
...those things we can continue to take them for granted
...world so I'm just going to hit the button here get this guy running.
It would be great if we waited until this worked and then.
...would...more appropriate time to clap and,
then let's switch over to input five and let's make sure that
this guys running so hey there's the app the app is actually running that's a good thing...on.
...the applications running you can see the clock ticking
on getting data in real-time that's fantasticgoing to let this run for a little bit
...some data and meanwhile I'm going to pop open
...open a website here.
The application part is easy but the typing the right thing into internet explorer thing is much harder
format ok so
when you see here is an open-source project that we've developed at microsoft called
connect the dots I'm using connect the dots is a very easy onramp into the
...your io t infrastructure that sam and his team or
building so this gives me a very easy way to take these properties that you saw me collect on this
device packages them up and do a
...document and...sends that...rest api
...through the through set of libraries that connect the dots offers
...makes it really easy for me to just kind of send this data up so you can see m
collecting data right here as time goes forward it's a little let's see if let's see
if I can perturbed if I can perturbed the data may be by blowing on this thing?
...seattle okay...perturbed I had garlic for lunch and I would be perturbed
toactually you can see...interesting bug here which is at about a...twenty
that humidity flips over back to zero again so that's why you see that weird drop in the
graph so, this data is going from my machine again...rest api calls
...document it goes in through event hub which sam
described to you and then from event hub this gets put industry analytics and
also get put into as your machine learning so using machine learning you see some
little polka dots appearing on this graph if I were to hover over these what this
says is that this...dot is an anomaly in the data detected by
asher machine learning so I started this I let it run for a little bit it learned as it was
collecting data what sort of normal looks like and then as I blew into it I
created some conditions that made it look not normal anymore so that as your machine learning kind of
...that and was able to them report backed me and I, you know,
...not blown into this that will maybe give-me reason to pause and I think this is a common pattern
we're saying with...anomaly...predictive maintenance your machine learning that's right?
Okay, and,...switch back to back to slides.
We talked about all join a little bit earlier
...gavin to the session earlier this is the idea that no matter what kind of device I had no matter
who makes it they should all just be able to work together in a secure way.
And,...and, then one other thing I wanted to mention
...you guys is this idea of complete life-cycle management from the time I
...role device into my enterprises included as a part of my
inventory configure it manage the...software that runs on that device
...assistance...something goes wrong with that device and finally take it out of my
...after a period of time we've got both the support within the operating system
as well as ... our tools with system center and into or
third-party mgm tools this is all happens over open protocol called
...so you can manage all of these devices and very consistent way.
And, to learn more few sessions point you
two-one is pure richardson session on all of the io to devices
all of the windows...additions my session tomorrow which will be more focused on
the maker space retail session I mention which is on friday and you
can catch gavin session on the recording.
All right does great steve so,
my little board went to sleep it's now back up you can come up and take a look at it really
highlights the need to be able to remotely manage these devices
I'm being told I can I can show it.
All right screens.
And, now push my button.
Go back over to.
And,...back-up yet.
...changed on here I can see it moi.
Like this segment...again it appears the drinks have gone
...one dollar...my kind of that's my kind of embed device.
But, this really highlights the need to be able to remotely manage devices because this isn't
something you'd want to go... rolla truck for you'd want to just go send a signal.
...okay we just got this...so.
...ending on...note a thank you all for coming we've got a bunch
of great stuff coming up and I ot that will be disclosing later this
...well we appreciate all your support and...have a great build thank you.